Guide to the William Ames Collection ARS.0072
Archive of Recorded Sound
William Ames Collection
1947-1966
ARS.0072
Ames, William T.
1 box: 22 open reel tapes
Archive of Recorded Sound
Tape recordings of works by composer William Ames.
Access
Open for research; material must be requested at least two business days in advance of intended use. Contact the Archive for assistance.
Biography
American composer William Thayer Ames (1901-1987) was born in Cambridge, Massachusetts and wrote his first compositions while attending Harvard in the early 1920s. After graduating with a degree in music, Ames studied with Nadia Boulanger in Paris, and returned to the United States to teach at the Eastman School of Music. In 1940 Harvard awarded Ames a masters degree, and he lived for a time in New York. It was during this period that a program of his works was performed at Carnegie Hall. In 1954 Ames was appointed to the faculty at Cornell's dance department (pieces for dance and theater were almost as important to him as his chamber music, orchestral works and operas). Following spells in New Hampshire and New York, Ames retired to the peaceful setting of Mendocino, California in 1965, where he spent the rest of his life writing music.
Scope and Contents
The William Ames Collection consists of twenty-two tape reels of performances of Ames compositions, some with Ames' own involvement. Documentation of these performances is limited; all information from the tape boxes has been transcribed. Some performers are identified, including sopranos Barbara Troxell and Antonia Lavanne, tenor Earl Rogers, violinist Max Pollikoff and 'cellist George Finckl. Nine of the reels are professional transfers from instantaneous discs by Stone Sound Studio in Woodstock, New York. It is likely, however, that all reels are copies and that the originals exist elsewhere.
Related Collections
Special Collections at the Eastman School of Music holds the William Ames Collection, which contains the composer's papers, music and recordings.
- 1. Unnumbered reels
  - Augurs: opera in one act for two sopranos and baritone. Ames on piano, with Suzy, Marilyn, Dino, 1959; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Concerto for clarinet and orchestra; Prologue for flute, horn and strings, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Improvisation, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Junk; Summer Elegy, 1 7" open reel tape folders (Audio 1)
  - Piece for flute and piano; Trio for flute, violin and viola; Improvisations for piano; Piano-percussion sketches, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Quartet for oboe, violin, viola and 'cello; Two movements for bassoon quartet, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Quest; Mad woman of Chaillot, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Sixth string quartet; Piano quartet, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Sonata for violin and piano; Composition for 10 instruments, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Songs: Earl Rogers, Antonia Lavanne, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Trio for flute, oboe and 'cello. Two performances: Carnegie Hall recital 1958, Town Hall 1964, 1958-1964; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Trio for piano, violin and 'cello, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Trio for violin, viola and 'cello; Waltz "Spring song", 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
- 2. Numbered reels (disc transfers)
  - Reel 1. Tree of bane; two preludes for piano (1948-05-01); Rhapsody for piano, American Festival (1952-02-18); The darkness rolls upward / Barbara Troxell, 1948-1952; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Reel 3. Music for film, "Philip Evergood"; The jester, 1 5" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Reel 4. Composition for modern dance 1-4 (same as reel 2 but other pressings), 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Reel 5. Movement for woodwind quintet; Trio for violin, 'cello and piano, 1956-1957; 1 5" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Reel 6. Composers Forum concert. Song group #1; Song group #2, 1 5" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Reel 7. Song cycle, "Pygmalion" (songs 1-6), 1946-03-24; 1 5" open reel tape (Audio 1)
  - Reel 8. 1966 Bennington Composers Conference, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Rigamarole - Among the gods - Bereft - Stopping by the woods - A blue butterfly day - A peck of gold - A minor bird / Earl Rogers, tenor; Sketch for violin and piano / Max Pollikoff, violin; 5 songs / Ethel Leuning
  - Reel 9. American Festival, etc., 1947-1958; 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)
    Patch of old snow - Meeting - Rapid and vansit - Now close the window - Star moss / Ethel Luening, soprano; 1958 American Festival (1958-02-18): No city - Dream pang / Barbara Troxell; 1947 American Festival WNYC (1947-02-21): Twilight - Winter apples - Sand paintings - Outwitted - Nocturne from suite for 'cello and piano; 1952 American Festival (1952-02-18): Rhapsody for piano - The darkness rolls upward / Barbara Troxell; No city; Dream pang
  - Reel 10. Suite for 'cello and piano (Prelude, Nocturne, Scherzo, Epilogue) / George Finckel, cello, 1 7" open reel tape (Audio 1)